我们已经看过了历史上的几种密码
Now that we've seen a few examples of
historic ciphers, all of which are badly
【ikamusume酱 译注】
它们都可以被严重地破解。
现在我们要看一些设计得好得多的密码了
broken, we're going to switch gears and
talk about ciphers that are much better
不过在这之前，我想先准确定义什么是密码
designed. But before we do that, I want to,
first of all, define more precisely what a
首先，记住密码实际上是由
cipher is. So first of all, a cipher is
actually, remember a cipher is made up of
两个算法组成的
它们是加密算法和解密算法
two algorithms. There's an encryption
algorithm and a decryption algorithm. But
但事实上，密码定义为一个三元组
全体可能的密钥，
in fact, a cipher is defined over a
triple. So the set of all possible keys,
记为花体的K，有时我叫它密钥空间
which I'm going to denote by script K, and
sometimes I'll call this the key space,
密钥空间是全体可能的密钥的集合
有个全体可能明文的集合
it's the set of all possible keys. There's
this set of all possible messages and this
还有全体密文的集合。好的
这个三元组某种意义上定义了
set of all possible ciphertexts. Okay, so
this triple in some sense defines the
密码的环境。密码本身是
environment over which the cipher is
defined. And then the cipher itself is a
一对算法E和D。E是加密算法
pair of efficient algorithms E and D. E is
the encryption algorithm; D is the
D是解密算法。当然，E输入密钥和明文
输出密文
decryption algorithm. Of course, E takes
keys and messages. And outputs ciphertexts.
解密算法输入密钥和密文，输出明文
And the decryption algorithm takes
keys and ciphertexts. Then outputs messages.
只要求这两算法一致
And the only requirements is that these
algorithms are consistent. They satisfy
它们要满足正确的性质
所以，对明文空间里的每一条信息
what's called the correctness property. So
for every message in the message space.
对密钥空间里的每一个密钥
最好是如果我用密钥K加密明文
And every key. In the key space, it had
better be the case that if I encrypt the
然后我用同样的密钥K解密
message with the key K and then I decrypt
using the same key K I had better get back
我最好能回到最初的明文信息
这个方程就叫
the original message that I started with.
So this equation here is what's called the
一致性方程，每个密码都要满足它
consistency equation and every cipher has
to satisfy it in order to be a cipher
否则就没法解密了
注意一下，我这里给
otherwise it's not possible to decrypt.
One thing I wanted to point out is that I
“有效”这个词打了引号
原因是有效这个词
put the word efficient here in quotes. And
the reason I do that is because efficient
不同人理解不同。如果你倾向理论
means different things to different
people. If you're more inclined towards
多项式时间就算有效的。那么算法E和D
theory, efficient means runs in polynomial
time. So algorithms E and D have to run in
必须在多项式时间内完成，
具体时间取决于输入的规模
polynomial time in the size of their
inputs. If you're more practically
如果你倾向应用
在特定时间内完成才算有效
inclined, efficient means runs within a
certain time period. So for example,
例如，算法E可能需要在一分钟内
algorithm E might be required to take
under a minute to encrypt a gigabyte of
加密1G的数据。不管是哪个
“有效”这个词你可以自己
data. Now either way, the word efficient
kind of captures both notions and you can
来决定如何诠释它
interpret it in your head whichever way
you'd like. I'm just going to keep
我只是给“有效”打上引号
referring to it as efficient and put
quotes in it as I said if you're theory
你可以很理论地认为是多项式时间
inclined think of it as polynomial time,
otherwise think of it as
也可以认为是有时间限制的
我想说的另一点是关于算法E的
concrete time constraints. Another comment
I want to make is in fact algorithm E.
E经常是一个随机算法，意思是
It's often a randomized algorithm. What
that means is that as your encrypting
当你加密信息时，
算法E自己生成二进制随机数
messages, algorithm E is gonna generate
random bits for itself, and it's going to
它将使用这些随机数来加密给定的明文信息
use those random bits to actually encrypt
the messages that are given to it. On the
另一方面，解密算法是确定算法，换句话说
other hand the decrypting algorithm is
always deterministic. In other words given
密钥和密文输出总是一致的
the key and the ciphertext output is
always the same. Doesn't depend on any
算法不依赖于任何随机性
好，我们现在更好地理解了密码
randomness that's used by the algorithm.
Okay, so now that we understand what a
我想给大家展示安全密码的第一个例子
cipher is better, I want to kind of show
you the first example of a secure cipher.
它叫做一次性密码本。由Vernam在20世纪初设计
It's called a one time pad. It was designed
by Vernam back at the beginning of the
在我解释这个密码之前，我们先用
twentieth century. Before I actually
explain what the cipher is, let's just
刚才介绍的术语来阐述之
state it in the terminology that we've
just seen. So the message space for the
Vernam密码，即一次性密码本的明文空间
同其密文空间一样
Vernam cipher for the one-time pad is the
same as the ciphertext space which is
是全体n位二进制字符串的集合。
这就是说所有二进制0,1字符串
just the set of all n bit binary strings.
This, this just means all sequences of
密钥空间和明文空间是一样的
bits, of zero one characters. The key
space is basically the same as the message
也是所有n位二进制字符串
space which is again simply the n bit of
all binary strings. So a key in the one
那么一次性密码本的密钥就是一个随机字符串
它是一随机的二进制序列
time pad is simply a random big string,
it's a random sequence of bits. That's as
密钥与待加密的明文等长，与明文等长
long as the message to be encrypted, as
long as the message. Okay, now that we've
好，现在我们知道了密码是如何定义的
specified kind of what's the cipher's
defined over we can actually specify how
我们能指定这密码是如何工作的
很简单的，本质上，密文
the cipher works and it's actually really
simple. So essentially the ciphertexts.
也就是用特定密钥加密明文的结果
Which is the result of encrypting a
message with a particular key, is simply
密文就是密钥和明文的异或结果
就是K异或M。我们看个例子
the XOR of the two. Simply K XOR M. Let's see a quick example of
还记得异或吗？就是这个带环的加号
this. Remember that XOR, this plus
with a circle. XOR means addition
异或就是模2加法。那么如果我取
一特定信息，比如0110111
modulo two. So if I take a particular
message, say, 0110111. And it take a
再取一个特定密钥，比如1011001
当我计算信息的加密结果时
particular key, say 1011001. When I
compute the encryption of the message
使用密钥，我只需计算两字符串的异或
using this key, all I do is I
compute the XOR of these two
换句话说，我逐位计算模2加法
strings. In other words, I do addition
module or two bit by bit. So I get one,
所以我得到1101110，即密文
那我怎么解密呢？
one, zero, one, one, one, zero. That's a
ciphertext. And then how do I decrypt? I
我想可以做同样的事情。使用特定密钥解密
guess they could do kind of the same
thing. So they decrypt a cipher text using
只需计算密钥和密文的异或
a particular key. What I do is I XOR the
key and the ciphertext again. And so all
我们只需证明它满足一致性要求
we have to verify is that it satisfies the
consistency requirements. And I'm going to
我慢慢地证一遍，从今往后
我将假定大家都能易证这个性质
do this slowly once and then from now on,
I'm going to assume this is all, simple to
那么我们要保证如果我用特定密钥解密
you. So we're gonna make, we're gonna have
to make sure that if I decrypt a cipher
我最好能还原明文信息M
text, that was encrypted using a
particular key, I had better get back the
这里发生了什么？让我们看一下
message M. So what happens here? Well,
let's see. So if I look at the encryption
用K和M的加密，就是使用了异或的定义
of k and m, this is just k XOR m by
definition. What's the decryption of k XOR
K异或M用K如何解密？
就是 K异或（K异或M）
m using k? That's just k XOR (k XOR
m). And so since I said that XOR is
由于异或是模2加法，加法有可结合性
于是这就等于（K异或K）异或M
addition modulo two, addition is
associative, so this is the same as (k XOR k)
显然K异或K就是0，0异或任意M还是M
XOR m, which is simply as you know k XOR k is a zero, and zero XOR anything
好的，这就证明了一次性密码本确是密码
is simply m. Okay, so this actually shows
that the one-time pad is in fact a cipher,
但它并没有解释其安全性
but it doesn't say anything about the
security of the cipher. And we'll talk
我们待会将讨论密码的安全性
首先，我先问一个简单问题
about security of the cipher in just a
minute. First of all, let me quickly ask
确保大家都跟上了
you a question, just to make sure we're
all in sync. Suppose you are given a
假设有明文信息M，使用一次性密码本加密
message m and the encryption of that
message using the one time pad. So all
你有明文和密文。问题是
you're given is the message and the cipher
text. My question to you is, given this
给定M和C，你能否解出生成密文C用的
pair m and c, can you actually figure out
the one-time pad key that was used in the
一次性密码本的密钥？
creation of c from m?
我希望大家都发现了，
给定明文和密文
So I hope all of you
realize that in fact, given the message in
这是很容易还原出密钥的
the cipher text it's very easy to recover
what the key is. In particular the key is
密钥就是M异或C。我们来证明之
如果大家觉得这不是很显然
simply M XOR C. Then we'll see that if
it's not immediately obvious to you we'll
在讲座稍后讨论之。好的
see why that's, the case, a little later
in the talk, in the lecture. Okay alright
从性能的观点看，一次性密码本很不错
so the 1-time pad is a really cool from a
performance point of view all you're doing
你可以以极快的速度异或密钥和信息
is you exo-ring the key in the message so
it's a super, super fast. Cypher for
可以加解密很长的信息。但很不幸
encrypting and decrypting very long
messages. Unfortunately it's very
这个方法在实际中很难使用
原因是密钥需要与明文一样长
difficult to use in practice. The reason
it's difficult to use is the keys are
所以如果Alice和Bob想安全通信
essentially as long as the message. So if
Alice and Bob want to communicate
Alice想给Bob发送一条信息
securely, so you know Alice wants to send
a message end to Bob, before she begins
在她发送信息的第一位之前
她需要给Bob传送一个密钥
even sending the first bit of the message,
she has to transmit a key to Bob that's as
密钥和明文一样长
如果Alice有办法安全地传给Bob一个密钥
long as that message. Well, if she has a
way to transmit a secure key to Bob that's
这个密钥和明文一样长，她就可以
用这个办法把明文直接传了
as long as the message, she might as well
use that same mechanism to also transmit
所以事实上密钥和明文一样长
the message itself. So the fact that the
key is as long as the message is quite
是很有问题的
这也使得一次性密码本在实际中很难用
problematic and makes the one-time pad
very difficult to use in practice.
虽然我们将看到一次性密码本背后的思想
Although we'll see that the idea behind
the one-time pad is actually quite useful
实际上是很有用的，我们稍后还会讨论
但我现在想关注一下安全
and we'll see that a little bit later. But
for now I want to focus a little bit on
那么之前的问题是，
为什么一次性密码本是安全的？
security. So the obvious questions are,
you know, why is the one-time pad secure?
为什么它是个好的密码？
为回答这个问题，我们首先要回答
Why is it a good cypher? Then to answer
that question, the first thing we have to
什么是安全的密码？
什么让密码变得安全？
answer is, what is a secure cipher to
begin with? What is a, what makes cipher
好，为研究密码的安全性
我们必须讲一点
secure? Okay, so the study, security of
ciphers, we have to talk a little bit
信息论的内容。事实上
第一个研究密码安全性的人
about information theory. And in fact the
first person, to study security of ciphers
非常有名，他是Claude Shannon
信息论之父
rigorously. Is very famous, you know, the
father of information theory, Claude
1949年，他发表了一篇著名论文
Shannon, and he published a famous paper
back in 1949 where he analyzes the
(Communication Theory of Secrecy Systems
第10小节 Perfect Secrecy)
文章里他分析了一次性密码本
Shannon定义的安全的基本想法如下
security of the one-time pad. So the idea
behind Shannon's definition of security is
如果你得到密文了
the following. Basically, if all you get
to see is the cypher text, then you should
从中你得不出一点点关于明文的信息
learn absolutely nothing about the plain
text. In other words, the cypher text
换句话说，密文不揭露任何明文的信息
should reveal no information about the
plain text. And you see why it took
为什么让创立信息论的人提出这个观点？
someone who invented information theory to
come up with this notion because you have
因为必须形式化地定义明文的信息
to formulize, formally explain what does
information about the plain text actually
好，那是Shannon的贡献
我给大家看一看Shannon的定义
mean. Okay so that's what Shannon did and
so lemme show you Shannon's definition,
我慢点写。Shannon说
I'll, I'll write it out slowly first. So
what Shannon said is you know suppose we
假设我们有加解密算法E和D
定义在三元组(K,M,C)上，之前提过
have a cypher E D that's defined over
triple K M and C just as before. So KM and
K为密钥空间，M为明文空间，C为密文空间
C define the key space, the message space
and the cypher text space. And when we say
我们说密码是完美安全的
that the cypher text sorry we say that the
cypher has perfect secrecy if the
如果如下条件成立：
对M中任意两个明文M0和M1
following condition holds. It so happens
for every two messages M zero and M1 in
我只要求它们俩的长度相同
the message space. For every two messages
the only requirement I'm gonna put on
只有这一个要求，我们很快将看到
为什么这个要求是必需的
these messages is they have the same
length. Yeah so we're only, we'll see why
对于每一个密文空间里的密文
this requirement is necessary in just a
minute. And for every cyphertext, in the
对于每一对明文和密文
cyphertext space. Okay? So for every pair
of message and for every cipher
如下概率关系成立
text, it had better be the case that, if I
ask, what is the probability that,
给定C，用K加密M0，对吧？
encrypting M zero with K, woops.
Encrypting M zero with K gives C, okay? So
如果密钥K随机选取，我们加密M0
how likely is it, if we pick a random key?
How likely is it that when we encrypt M
结果得到C的可能性有多少？这个概率
应当与我们加密M1得到c一样
zero, we get C. That probability should be
the same as when we encrypt M1. Okay, so
好的，所以加密M1得到c的概率
the probability of encrypting M1 and
getting c is exactly the same as the
等于加密M0得到c的概率
probability of encrypting M0 and
getting c. And just as I said where the
如我所说，密钥分布在密钥空间上
key, the distribution, is over the
distribution on the key. So, the key is
密钥分布是均匀的。所以k在K上均匀分布
我经常写个上面有r的箭头
uniform in the key space. So k is uniform
in K. And I'm often going to write k arrow
表示k是个均匀分布在密钥空间上的随机变量
with a little r above it to denote the
fact that k is a random variable that's
好的，这是Shannon定义的主要部分
uniformly sampled in the key space k.
Okay, this is the main part of Shannon's
我们来想想这个定义到底说的是什么
definition. And let's think a little bit
about what this definition actually says.
这两个概率相等的意思是什么？
So what does it mean that these two
probabilities are the same? Well, what it
意思是，如果我是攻击者
我截获了一段密文c
says is that if I'm an attacker and I
intercept a particular cypher text c, then
实际中，密文是M0的加密结果的概率
in reality, the probability that the
cypher text is the encryption of M0 is
与是M1的加密结果的概率严格相等
exactly the same as the probability that
it's the encryption of M1. Because
因为这些概率是相等的
如果我有截获的密文C
those probabilities are equal. So if I
have, all I have the cypher text C that's
我也无从得知这密文是从M0来的
all I have intercepted I have no idea
whether the cypher text came from M zero
还是从M1来的，因为获得C的概率相等
or the cypher text came from M one because
again the probability of getting C is
无论是加密M0还是M1
equally likely whether M zero is being
encrypted or M one is being encrypted. So
所以这里我们又重申了一遍定义
我想把这些定义写得更清楚些
here, we have the definition stated again.
And I just wanna write these properties
我们把这个定义再写一遍。这个定义的意思是
again more precisely. So let's write this
again. So what does this definition
如果我有一段特定的密文，
我无法得知它是怎么来的
means is that if I am given a particular
cipher text, I can't tell where it came
我无法得知被加密的明文是M0还是M1
from. I can't tell if it's, if the message
that was encrypted. Is either M zero or M
事实上，这个性质对所有明文信息都成立
对所有M0
one and in fact, this property is true for
all messages. For all these M zero, for
所有M1，我无法得知C是从M0或M1来
all M zero and M ones. So not only can I
not tell if 'c' came from M zero or M one,
也无法得知是不是从M2,M3,M4,M5来的
I can't tell if it came from M two or M
three or M four or M five because all of
因为它们生成C的概率都一样
them are equally likely to produce the
cypher text'c'. So what this means really
这意味着，如果你使用一次性密码本加密
is that if you're encrypting messages with
a one time pad then in fact the most
不管攻击者有多聪明，多强大
powerful adversary, I don't really care
how smart you are, the most powerful
其也无法得知任何关于明文的信息
adversary. Can learn nothing about the
plain text, learns nothing about the plain
换种说法，从密文的角度来看
text. From the cypher text. So to say it
in one more way, basically what this
这证明了对于完美安全的密码
任何惟密文攻击无效
proves is that there's no, there's no
cypher text-only attack on a cypher that
现在，攻击者不单单是攻击密码
has perfect secrecy. Now, cypher attacks
actually aren't the only attacks possible.
事实上还有其他类型的攻击者
And in fact, other attacks may be
possible, other attacks may be possible.
好的，现在我们更好地理解了完美安全
Okay. Now that we understand what perfect
secrecy, means, the question is, can we
问题是，我们能建立完美安全的密码吗？
build ciphers that actually have perfect
secrecy? And it turns out that we don't
其实我们不必看得太远
一次性密码本就具备完美安全
have to look very far, the one time
pad in fact has perfect secrecy. So I
我想给大家证明Shannon最初的结果
want to prove to you this is Shannon's first
results and I wanna prove this fact to
这个证明很简单，所以我们上
you, it's very simple proof so let's go
ahead and look at it and just do it. So we
我们需要解释一下E(k,m0)=c的概率是多少
need to kind of interpret what does that
mean, what is this probability that E K M
不难看出，对每条明文和密文信息
Zero is equal to C. So it's actually not that
hard to see that for every message and
用密钥k加密m结果等于c的概率
every cyphertext the probability that the
encryption of M under a key K the
密钥k根据定义是随机选择的
probability that, that's equal to C, the
probability that our random choice of key
那就是所有密钥的个数。好的
by definition. All that is, is basically
the number of keys. Okay, instruct Kay.
如果我用密钥k加密m，会得到c。
我数出所有密钥的个数
Such that, well. If I encrypt m with k
I get c. So I literally count the number
然后我除以密钥的个数，得到的就是概率吧？
of keys and I divide by the total number
of keys. Right? That's what it means, that
如果我随机选择一个密钥
这个密钥将m映射到c
if I choose a random key, that key maps m
to c. Right. So it's basically the number
概率就是能将n映射到c的密钥数
除以全体密钥的个数
of key that map n to c divided by the
total number of keys. This is its
假设我们有一个密码，对所有明文和密文
probability. So now suppose that we had a
cypher such that for all messages and all
如果我看这个数，k的数目
cypher texts, it so happens that if I look
at this number, the number of k, k, and k,
满足E(k,m)=c。换句话说
我要寻找能将m映射到c的密钥数
such that e, k, m is equal to c. In other
words, I'm looking at the number of keys
假设这个数是个常数
that map m to c. Suppose this number
happens to be a constant. So say it
比如它会是2，3或10，15
happens to be two, three, or ten or
fifteen. It just hap, happens to be an
它会是个常数。如果是这种情况
根据定义，对于所有m0和m1
absolute constance. If that's the case,
then by definition, for all m0 and m1 and
和所有c，这个概率都是一样的
因为分母一样
for all c, this probability has to be the
same because the denominator is the same,
且分子也一样，它就是个常数
the numerator is the same, it's just as
constant, and therefore the probability is
所以对所有n和c，概率一致
如果这个性质满足
always the same for all n and c. And so if
this property is true, then the cypher has
该密码一定具备完美安全
好的，那我们来看看定量看看
to have, the cypher has perfect secrecy.
Okay, so let's see what can we say about
一次性密码本的这一性质
问大家一个问题
this quantity for the one time pad. So the
sec-, so, the question to you is, if I
如果我有一条密文信息，
有多少可能的一次性密码本的密钥
have a message in a cipher-text, how many
one time pad keys are there that
满足映射的结果为密文c？
换句话说，有多少这样的密钥k
map, this message ends, so the ciphertext
C? So, in other words, how many keys are
满足m异或k等于c？
那么我们希望大家都回答的是1
there, such that M XOR K is equal to C?
So I hope you've all answered one. And
我们来看看为什么是这样
对于一次性密码本，我们有
let's see why that's the case. For the one
time pad, if we have that, the encryption
用k加密m等于c，但是根据定义
of K of M under K is equal to C. But
basically, well, by definition, that
这意味着k异或m等于c，但这也说明
implies that K XOR M is equal to C. But
that also simply says that K has to equal
k一定等于m异或c。是的，
我在等式两边同时异或m
to M XOR C. Yes, I just X over both
sides by M and I get that K must equal the
得到k等于m异或c，对吧？这意味着
对于一次性密码本，事实上
M XOR C. Okay? So what that says is
that, for the one time pad, in fact, the
密钥k的数目，满足E(k,m)=c的，就一个
number of keys, in K, shows the EKM, is
equal to C. That simply is one, and this
这点对所有密文信息都成立
又根据我们之前说的
holds for all messages in cipher text. And
so, again, by what we said before, it just
一次性密码本有完美安全
这个完美安全的证明
says that the one time pad has, perfect
secrecy. Perfect secrecy and that
是非常简单的，是个非常简单的引理
completes the proof of this
very, very simple. Very, very simple
有趣的是，即使这个引理如此易证
lemma. Now the funny thing is that
even though this lemma is so simple to
事实上它还证明了一个很强的结论
prove in fact it proves a pretty powerful
statement again. This basically says for
对一次性密码本，没有惟密文攻击
the one time pad, there is no
cypher text only attack. So, unlike the
与替换式密码、Vigenere密码、转轴机不同
substitution cipher, or the vigenere
cipher, or the roller machines, all those
后面这些都不能抵抗惟密文攻击
我们刚刚证明了对于一次性密码本
could be broken by ciphertext-only attack.
We've just proved that for the one-time
惟密文攻击就是不可能。给定密文
pad, that's simply impossible. Given the
cyphertext, you simply learn nothing about
你无从得知明文。但是，可以看到事还没完
the plaintext. However, as we can see,
this is simply not the end of the story. I
完了吗？感觉这门课现在上完了
mean, are we done? I mean, basically,
we're done with the course now, cuz we
因为我们有了一个方法去加密了
而且攻击者无法还原任何信息
have a way. To encrypt, so that an
attacker can't recover anything about our
用我们的方法。所以这课可能已经上完
但事实上，我们会看到
method. So maybe we're done with the
course. But in fact, as we'll see, there
还有其他类型的攻击。实际上
一次性密码本并非安全的
are other attacks. And, in fact, the one
time pad is actually not such a
实际上还有其他可能的攻击
secure cipher. And in fact, there are
other attacks that are possible, and we'll
我们很快就会看到，对吧？强调一下
完美安全并不意味着
see that shortly. Okay? I emphasize again
the fact that it has perfect secrecy does
一次性密码本在实际使用中是安全的
not mean that the one time pad is the
secure cypher to use. Okay. But as we said
好。就像我们之前说的，一次性密码本的问题
在于它的密钥非常的长
the problem with the one time pad is that
the secret key is really long. If you had
如果你有安全传递密钥的方法给对方
a way of communicating the secret key
over to the other side. You might as well
你也可以使用那个办法直接传递信息了
use that exact same method to also
communicate the message to the other side,
根本不需要密码，对吧？
in which case you wouldn't need a cypher
to begin with. Okay? So the problem again
所以问题是一次性密码本的密钥太长
显然，问题是是否有其他密码
is the one time pad had really long keys
and so the obvious question is are there
也具备完美安全，却有短得多的密钥？
other cyphers that has perfect secrecy and
possibly have much, much shorter keys?
有个坏消息是，Shannon在证完
一次性密码本具有完美安全之后
Well, so the bad news is the Shannon,
after proving that the one-time pad has
又证明了另一个定理，告诉我们
perfect secrecy, proved another theorem
that says that in fact if a cypher has
如果一个密码是完美安全的，
其全体密钥数，不少于其能处理的明文数
perfect secrecy, the number of keys in the
cypher must be at least the number of
好的，特别地，这意味着
messages that the cypher can handle. Okay,
so in particular, what this means is if I
如果我们有完美安全，那么密钥数
have perfect secrecy. Then necessarily the
number of keys, or rather the length of my
或说我的密钥长度必须不小于明文长度
key, must be greater than the length of
the message. So, in fact, since the one
由于一次性密码本的等号满足条件
它实际上是一个最优的加密
time pad satisfies us with equality, the
one time pad is an optimal, cipher that
满足完美安全，对吧？
has perfect secrecy, okay? So basically,
what this shows is that this is an
这是个有趣的观点。一次性密码本很有趣
interesting notion. The one time pad is an
interesting cipher. But, in fact, in
但事实上它很难用，很难付诸实践
reality, it's actually quite hard to use.
It's hard to use in practice, again,
因为过长的密钥
尽管这个完美安全的观点很有趣
because of these long keys. And so this
notion of perfect secrecy, even though
它并没有告诉我们如何设计
it's quite interesting, basically says
that it doesn't really tell us the
既安全又实用的密码
我们将会看到，就像之前所说
practical cyphers are going to be secure.
And we're gonna see, but, as we said, the
一次性密码本的思想是很好的
在下一讲中我们会看到
idea behind the one time pad is quite good.
And we're gonna see, in the next lecture,
如何利用这一思想，设计一个实用的系统
how to make that into a practical
system.